<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Steam - a minimal theme for Hugo</title>
    <link>http://paarthneekhara.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Steam - a minimal theme for Hugo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 00:11:40 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://paarthneekhara.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Step Aside From The Race</title>
      <link>http://paarthneekhara.github.io/post/step-aside-from-the-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 00:11:40 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://paarthneekhara.github.io/post/step-aside-from-the-race/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;this-is-one-of-my-first-poems-and-my-personal-favourite&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is one of my first poems and my personal favourite.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Step aside from the race to think.&lt;br /&gt;
Relax and realize the purpose of the race&lt;br /&gt;
Think from an unconditioned perspective&lt;br /&gt;
Are we here to survive?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are we so desperate to keep the world moving?&lt;br /&gt;
Are we merely players in The Big Drama?&lt;br /&gt;
Being watched by an unknown audience&lt;br /&gt;
And we humans playing the role of fools and jokers&lt;br /&gt;
In the more sensible world around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this life a gift or a trap?&lt;br /&gt;
With luxuries merely the baits,&lt;br /&gt;
To catch the innocent beings&lt;br /&gt;
In this illusionary and deceiving world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think again before you rejoin the race&lt;br /&gt;
It’s destination unknown but it&amp;rsquo;s end assured&lt;br /&gt;
I rejoin the &amp;lsquo;Race&amp;rsquo; once more&lt;br /&gt;
Would think about it another day&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://paarthneekhara.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 18:07:07 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://paarthneekhara.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a passionate coder, currently pursuing my Bachelors degree in Computer Science from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iitr.ac.in/&#34;&gt;IIT Roorkee&lt;/a&gt;. I love solving real world problems. The journeys towards the solutions have been more .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been recently working on developing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rtifeed.com/about&#34;&gt;RTIFeed&lt;/a&gt;, a web platform to make authentic information available to the masses. This project has kept our team inspired and motivated for the last one year. I can talk endlessly about this project and its potential, but this page is about me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer Science wasn&amp;rsquo;t a planned affair for me. I started coding in 2013 and the more I explore, the more amazed I am at the sheer beauty of this subject. Machine Learning and Neural Networks in particular make me appreciate mathematics. It quenches the anxiety of my high school days when I felt topics like matrices, calculus were needless!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love travelling and photography. They complement each other perfectly. You can find some pictures of my travels and wildlife(mostly birds) &lt;a href=&#34;https://500px.com/paarthneekhara&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I started cycling a year ago and I actually wish a good night to my bike before I sleep! I love &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.strava.com/athletes/13254146&#34;&gt;riding around my home place&lt;/a&gt; - Dehradun, Uttarakhand. Amidst the magnificent Himalyas, this valley is a complete paradise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>