<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Paarth&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Paarth&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2016 12:34:19 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2016 12:34:19 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/projects/</guid>
      <description>Deep Learning Projects  ByteNet - Tensorflow Implemented the dilated convolutional ByteNet model of neural machine translation from the paper Neural Machine Translation in Linear Time .
 Text To Image Synthesis Using Thought Vectors Generative Adversarial Text to Image Synthesis using skip-thought vectors. Implemented the GAN-CLS algorithm from the paper Generative Adversarial Text to Image Synthesis and conditioned the model using text-embeddings from Skip Thought Vectors.
   Caption Generated Images     the flower shown has yellow anther red pistil and bright red petals    this flower has petals that are yellow, white and purple and has dark lines    the petals on this flower are white with a yellow center    this flower has a lot of small round pink petals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Important Things In Life Are Often Simple</title>
      <link>/post/simple-is-awesome/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2016 16:28:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/simple-is-awesome/</guid>
      <description>I remember these words from a lecture on Theory of Computation. The more you complicate a solution, the more specific it becomes to the problem being solved. The less you assume, the more you generalize. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep this article specific to Machine Learning and how simple things can do wonders!
Language There is something magical about how a little child learns a language. The child is not imparted any knowledge related to the semantics or the grammar of the language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 18:07:07 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a passionate coder, currently pursuing my Bachelors degree in Computer Science from IIT Roorkee. I love solving real world problems. The journeys towards the solutions have been more exciting than the destinations themselves.
I have been recently working on developing RTIFeed, a web platform to make authentic information available to the masses. This project has kept our team inspired and motivated for the last one year. I can talk endlessly about this project and its potential, but this page is about me!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lift Your Heart</title>
      <link>/post/lift-your-heart/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2014 14:55:57 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lift-your-heart/</guid>
      <description>The road was misty, dull and dark,
No one was there to lift my heart.
I&amp;rsquo;m all alone in that scary way,
The road less travelled is what they say.
Was I too brave to take a try?
On the road less travelled by.
Was I too strong to face the rocks?
I want a chance to turn the clocks.
If the choice was wrong, you make it right,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Step Aside From The Race</title>
      <link>/post/step-aside-from-the-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Oct 2012 00:11:40 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/step-aside-from-the-race/</guid>
      <description>This is one of my first poems and my personal favourite. 
Step aside from the race to think.
Relax and realize the purpose of the race
Think from an unconditioned perspective
Are we here to survive?
Why are we so desperate to keep the world moving?
Are we merely players in The Big Drama?
Being watched by an unknown audience
And we humans playing the role of fools and jokers</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>