<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Abouts on Paarth&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/about/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Abouts on Paarth&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 18:07:07 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 18:07:07 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I am a passionate coder, currently pursuing my Bachelors degree in Computer Science from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iitr.ac.in/&#34;&gt;IIT Roorkee&lt;/a&gt;. I love solving real world problems. The journeys towards the solutions have been more exciting than the destinations themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been recently working on developing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rtifeed.com/about&#34;&gt;RTIFeed&lt;/a&gt;, a web platform to make authentic information available to the masses. This project has kept our team inspired and motivated for the last one year. I can talk endlessly about this project and its potential, but this page is about me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer Science wasn&amp;rsquo;t a planned affair for me. I started coding in 2013 and the more I explore, the more amazed I am at the sheer beauty of this subject. Machine Learning and Neural Networks in particular make me appreciate mathematics. It quenches the anxiety of my high school days when I felt topics like matrices, calculus were needless!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love travelling and photography. They complement each other perfectly. You can find some pictures of my travels and wildlife(mostly birds) &lt;a href=&#34;https://500px.com/paarthneekhara&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I started cycling a year ago and I actually wish a good night to my bike before I sleep! I love &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.strava.com/athletes/13254146&#34;&gt;riding around my home place&lt;/a&gt; - Dehradun, Uttarakhand. Amidst the magnificent Himalyas, this valley is a complete paradise.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>